To this exercise video.
This exercise is about the derivation trees,
and furthermore, it's about the 'not' in Prolog.
We have been given a program up here.
The program consists of four lines, the Prolog
program.
We shall now draw the derivation trees for
the follow inquiries.
First of all, for disjoint of the list, [1,
2, 3], and the list [4,2].
Just as a short reminder, we have the not
here used in our program and also in these
queries.
But it's the same as the \+ which we've seen
in the lecture.
That was also mentioned that this is the same.
\+ Goal is the same as not (Goal).
We stick to this syntax here within these
videos.
Let's choose this first query here, disjoint
([1,2 3], [4, 2]).
This is the root of our tree.
We ask for this query, and now we try to think
about the-, or draw the derivation tree.
Therefore, we check all the queries we have
in order to search for possible follows of
this query here.
First of all, we have member X.
Our member and disjoint is not matching at
all, so we do not need to consider the member
fact or the other member line.
We can skip that one and we can go directly
to disjoint.
Disjoint doesn't match because we do not have
an empty list here.
The other line matches because we have a list
which consists of at least one element and
another list.
That's why we can consider this line.
We do a unification now, but first of all,
we do a renaming.
We have these new letters inserted here, and
now we do a unification with the left-hand
side of this line and our query.
Then we get a most general unifier.
X1 shall be replaced by 1.
XS1 by [2,3] and YS1 by [4,2].
We insert the most general unifier into the
right-hand side.
Now we get another query which consists of
this party now insert with the appropriate
well use from our most general unifier.
Now we consider the left-hand side of our
query because we have a conjunction here.
I separate by comma.
We consider first the first part.
The first part of this query is using not.
In this case, we go into a side branch considering
the knot.
We do this by just considering the query by
just considering the not part but removing
the not.
Now we are using (member (1, [4,2])), which
was here in the not.
We tried to match this one to our program.
There we have the first rule, which is a fact,
and which we cannot apply because there is
a mismatch with 1 and 4, but we can apply
it to the second line here.
Again, we do the renaming part, and then we
get a most general unifier replacing X or
matching X2 to 1.
I choose fresh names again here.
X2 by 1, Y2 by 4, and XS2 is matched by the
list of 2.
Then we can insert the right-hand side in
the next line and we get member (1, [2]).
Then we can again check where it is matching
in our program and then we see it's not matching
in the first line because 1 and 2 is not the
same so we get go to the second line where
we can match it again.
We get fresh … #00:06:01#.
We get a new most general unifier.
We replace X3 by 1, Y3 by 2, and XS3 by the
empty list so that we match exactly this part
here.
One the list 1,2 and the empty list, which
is exactly that here.
Then we can insert it into the right side.
We insert one in the empty list and we get
this query here.
Now we can check our program again and we
can check the member parts here.
We see that cannot match the first square
because it doesn't apply here for there is
now 1 in this list at the first element so
we cannot apply this fact here.
We cannot apply this rule here because well,
we have an empty list so we do not have a
list with no element and we cannot apply the
disjoint parts because they do not to match
with member.
That's why we are done here.
We cannot finish this query.
We cannot resolve this.
Because of this failure here, we can continue
in the other side here.
We use the disjoint part because this year
the inner part of the not was failing.
The not part was succeeding.
We can now look into the disjoint on the right-hand
side of the query above here.
Now we can match this again
with our rules again.
Just to be very clear, we cannot choose any
other branches here in these cases because
the member parts do not match with this joint.
For the same reason we couldn't continue here,
we cannot have other branches here as well.
Now we have this joint here as the next one
that we want to match.
We can skip the member rule rules and we can
look at the disjoint rules.
We can skip this one because it doesn't apply,
but this rule applies here.
We rename the arrivals, then we get our most
general unifier by saying X4 matches to 2
and XS4 matches to 3 and YS4 matches to [4,2].
That's our most general unifier.
Then we replace the right-hand side to get
the new query.
This again is not member part on the left-hand
side.
Because of the not, again, we have to handle
another sub query in a side branch.
We do put this member here into the side branch
and consider just this part.
Now we can match again here against our member
rules.
The first rule doesn't apply in this case,
but we can apply the second rule and match
it with the fresh arrivals here.
We get a most general unifier so that we can
match X5 by 2, Y5 to 4 and XS5 to 2.
We get
this most general unifier and we insert it
into the right-hand side, the member rule
here, the right-hand side.
We get a new query and then we can check for
this query again.
This time the first rule applies, or this
fact rather, this fact applies because X matches
here.
We can get almost general unifier by matching
X6 to 2 and XS6 to the empty list and thus
we succeed.
But because we succeed in the side branch,
we fail in the main branch.
That's where we stop our search because we
have failed.
Now we can check just if you missed something
in other branches.
In this disjoint branch we already checked
all our disjoint rules so there is nothing
left to check.
Also, the same applies in this disjoint query
here above.
We cannot have any more side branches.
This is the complete derivation tree for the
first query.
Let's get to the next part, which is the second
query.
This query is the disjoint ([1, 2, 3], Xs)
We proceed by matching this query to our program
rules.
We cannot match it to the member rules because
member and disjoint are not unifiable and
we cannot match it against this line.
Again, this doesn't match, but we can get
a most general unifier for the last rule here.
Get fresh names here and we match then get
a most general unifier here between disjoint
([1, 2, 3], Xs) and the left-hand side.
X1 is 1, XS1 is the list of 2 and 3 and YS1
matches to Xs.
Here two options possible.
We could replace YS1 by Xs or Xs by YS1.
I replace Xs by YS1 here.
We get a new query.
This one is the right-hand side just with
the replaced values from the most general
unifier.
Then we have again a query with the conjunction.
We have a comma in our query and we consider
the first part first.
This contains not, so we have to have a side
branch where we check the member and with
the inner part of the not.
The member (1, YS1) is checked in a side branch.
This one we match against our rules.
The first rule actually applies because we
can find actually an answer to this query
by picking the first rule.
We rename the variables here and get a most
general unifier because now we see it.
We can match X2 and replace it or match it
to 1.
When we do so, then we match YS1 to the list
of 1 and another list of XS2.
That's our result.
This is a fact.
That's why we are done here already.
We have checked this branch and know we are
done.
Because this is the side branch for the not,
we do not have to check any further.
We know there is a result, which immediately
means we fail in the main part of the query.
Thus, we have an arrow here in this case for
the disjoint ([1, 2, 3], XS) part.
This is quite surprising actually because
I think we didn't expect it when we see the
disjoint rules.
Or when you think about how disjoint might
work we could find it surprising.
Actually, we can find a list where there are
Xs such that these lists are not disjoint,
so it actually makes sense as well.
We can find a list where 1, 2, or 3 are actually
members, for instance.
Just endless where the 1 is a member.
We are done here with this part of the task.
Now there's the last part left, which is the
C part.
Now we considered not, not which was discussed
in the lecture already.
This is the part where we get an unexpected
result properly because it's not the double
negation logic that we have in product, but
it's this specific logic which happens here
in Prolog.
We choose this query here and then we will
see the results actually when you perform
it.
When we have this query here, then we have
in the first case a not at the beginning.
This query is in the not.
We open a side branch where we check the inner
part of the not.
This is again, a part where we have not at
the beginning and there's something inside.
Again, we open another side branch where we
check what's inside the not.
Now we check the disjoint here.
The disjoint Xs for 2.
We cannot apply the member rules, but we can
apply the disjoint.
We can apply the fact here in fact already
because Xs can be the empty list.
We can apply this rule here and then we are
done already.
We replace the arrivals in our query using
the most general unifier and then we are actually
done already.
This one is true.
We have got the success.
Then we fail in this case because we are of
the not.
Because we fail in this case because of the
not, we succeed in this case and the result
of our query is actually true.
We do not get results for access here in this
case because access is checked inside here.
While we could find the empty list here as
a result but we do not actually get the result
because the side queries are what we replace
inside here is withdrawn because the arrival
is bound inside, which is discussed in more
detail in the lecture.
We are just getting the true here and now
actually reliable spec from Prolog.
That was the third part of the task.
We are done with this exercise task.